Taft, Philip Papers 5541
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series II. Research/Subject Files
  - Foreign - Germany, 1933-1960 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    Letter from Leo Werts, Director, Manpower Division, Office of Military Government for Germany, to CIO Director of Department for International Affairs re political maneuvering with Soviet delegate over foreign trade union contacts in Germany, September 19, 1947, 3 pages; "The Crisis in Europe: Program For Germany - Declaration of the Executive Council, AFL, May11, 1950," a 10-point plan, 2 pages; "Report on Germany" by Jay Lovestone, Secretary AFL Delegation in behalf of George Harrison and David Dubinsky, AFL Delegates to London E.R.P. Trade Union Conference re conditions in Berlin under Soviet authority, conference with General Clay, 5 pages, n.d.; confidential letter from Secretary of Labor to Secretary of National Defense re "Recommendations for Immediate Action to Strengthen Democratic Elements in German Trade Unions," by Trade Union Advisory Committee on International Affairs, with comments by General Clay, March 3, 1948, 7 pages; booklets: 6 German-language publications, 5 English; notes
  - Foreign - Germany - Dismantling of Industry (Box 5, Folder 23)
    Letters to President Truman opposing dismantling of industry in Germany: from AFL President Green, November 24, 1947, 3 pages; from UAW President Walter Reuther, May 10, 1949, 2 pages, with attached 5 page analysis, "Dismantlement Program in Western Germany"; similar letter to Secretary of State Dean Acheson from Matthew Woll, Chairman, International Labor Relations Committee and Free Trade Union Committee, AFL, April 29, 1949, 3 pages; letters from AFL Special European representative Henry Rutz to various AFL officials and to U.S. Military Governor for Germany, 1947-48; two page "Memorandum ueber einen Plan eines Kongresses in Berlin," July 27, 1949; pamphlet "Institute of Industrial Relations - Collective Bargaining in Postwar Germany, University of California, 1952, 20 pages; notes
  - Foreign - Germany and Austria, 1923-1948 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    Correspondence between AFL International Labor Relations Committee and Free Trade Union Committee Chairman Matthew Woll and Secretary of the Army re paper supply to Germany, April 1948; letter to AFL President Green from German Social Democratic Party official thanking AFL for support of Marshall Plan, January 2, 1948; numerous reports form AFL representative Henry Rutz; notes
  - Foreign - Germany and Austria, 1949-1950 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    Letter to General Clay, Commander-in-chief, European Command, from AFL executive Matthew Eoll, re American policy in Germany, February 14, 1949, 9 pages; letter to High Commissioner McCloy from Matthew Eoll, urging administration of German coal industry by representatives of German labor, July 25, 1949, 3 pages; numerous reports from AFL representative Henry Rutz, 1949-1950; "Declaration of German Trade Union Federation on Radical Elements Threatening Democracy," March 6, 1950, 2 pages; notes
  - Foreign - Germany and Austria, 1950-1954 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    Correspondence between AFL executive Matthew Woll and Department of State officials re American policy in Germany, October-November 1951 (3 letters, 25 pages total); "Policy Governing Relations between HQ, U.S. Army, Europe and German Trade Unions," by command of Lieutenant General Eddy, October 16, 1952, 3 pages; notes
  - Foreign - Greece, 1947-1967 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    "Report on Greece," by AFL representative Irving Brown, n.d., 8 pages; articles, 1948 and 1967; notes
  - Foreign - Hungary, 1948-1956 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    Five booklets; notes.
  - Foreign - India, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    "Report on India," by AFL representative Irving Brown, April 1949, 8 pages
  - Foreign - Indonesia, 1949-1970 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    Articles; notes
  - Foreign - International Confederation of Free Trade Unions (ICFTU), 1949 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    "Free Trade Unions Form the I.C.F.T.U.," [c. December 1949], 22 pages; "Private and Confidential," ICFTU Executive Board minutes, first meeting, December 8-10, 1949, 14 pages; papers of Preparatory International Trade Union Committee; correspondence; notes
  - Foreign - International Confederation of Free Trade Unions, 1950-1968 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Correspondence between AFL executives George Meany and Matthew Woll re seeking intercession of the Pope on behalf of ICFTU, January 1950; "ICFTU Report of Meeting of Interim Finance Committee," January 17 and 18, 1950, 5 pages; "Report on Emergency Committee Meeting, March 16 to 18, 1950," by AFL representative Irving Brown, 5 pages; "ICFTU Emergency Committee, February 20-23, 1951," report by Irving Brown, 9 pages; AFL Executive Council minutes describing ICFTU meeting, January 26, 1951; "Statement by the Executive Council of the AFL," re Second World Congress of the ICFTU, May 18, 1951; report re Second World Congress of the ICFTU, by Irving Brown, August 2, 1951, 5 pages; "The Aims of Free Trade Unionism in the Struggle Against the Totalitarian Menace," report submitted by AFL Secretary-Treasurer George Meany to ICFTU Second World Congress, July 4-12, 1951, 6 pages; other statements by Congress delegates; correspondence re resignation of AFL officials Matthew Woll and David Dubinsky as U.N. consultants for ICFTU, April 1951)
  - Foreign - International Confederation of Free Trade Unions, 1950-1968 (Box 6, Folder 2cont.)
    letter from AFL President Green to ICFTU General Secretary Oldenbroek, protesting ICFTU appointment of representative for Singapore office, February 10, 1951; summary report by Irving Brown re ICFTU Executive Board session, December 2, 1951, 4 pages; "Notes on International Committee Meeting of the AFL," re difficulties with ICFTU, June 18, 1952, 16 pages; "From Irving Brown to George Meany," October 21, 1952, re upcoming ICFTU Executive Board Meeting, 4 pages; "Report by Irving Brown: Emergency Committee Meeting ICFTU," March 1-3, [1940s], 15 pages plus 2 page resolution on Latin America; "ICFTU European Regional Organization Conference," November 3-5, 1954, 5 pages plus 16 pages of appendices of resolutions and delegate lists; several ICFTU press releases, 1959; reprint from June 12, 1965 issue of AFL-CIO News: "The ICFTU: Estimate and Perspective," by George Meany; form letter "Relations between free trade union and Communist-controlled trade union organizations," from General Secretary of ICFTU, October 24, 1967, 2 pages plus 2 page appendix of Executive Board decisions; photocopies of articles from Free Trade Union News, 1965-68
  - Foreign - International Federation of Free Trade Unions (IFTU), 1888-1945 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Letter from AFL Executive Council to Federational Trade Union Congress in London re working conditions, October 27, 1888, 3 pages; correspondence, proceedings, proposals re Inter-Allied Labor Conference, London, September 17-19, 1918; letter to President Roosevelt from AFL President Green re World Economic Conference, May 1, 1933, 3 pages; "Interview with H. V. Tewson and Sir Walter Citrine," July 1, 1938, 8 pages; cablegrams and correspondence between Green, Citrine and AFL Executive Council re Anglo-Soviet Trade Union Committee, February-March 1942; "Anglo-Soviet Committee," 5 page manuscript, n.d., c. 1942; AFL Executive Council minutes re British Trades Union Congress, 1942-43; minutes of the IFTU, February 1 and 2, 1945, 17 pages; three page manuscript (possibly speech), unsigned, by AFL spokesperson re AFL refusal to participate in World Trade Union Conference, March 16, 1945; address by AFL representative Robert J. Watt to IFTU, January-February 1945, 15 pages; "What Happened at the London World Labor Conference," unsigned typescript with hand notation: "Statement issued by AFL on December 10, 1945," 9 pages; correspondence; notes.
  - Foreign - International Federation of Free Trade Unions, 1925-1953 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Five unsigned typescripts: four entitled "International Federation of Trade Unions," 3, 4, 5, and 6 pages, n.d., n.d., n.d., and 1942; one entitled "Effects of the War on Free Trade Unions in Europe," 1940, 6 pages; six issues of Trade Union World, monthly journal of the IFTU, 1943-44; June-July 1939 issue of The International Trade Union Movement, official organ of IFTU reporting on Eighth International Trade Union Congress; bulletins of the IFTU (August 12, 1941, 12 pages; July 1, 1942, 8 pages; December 1, 1944, 8 pages); "IFTU Report on Activities, 1943-1944," 13 pages, with unsigned typescript, n.d., based on the report, 7 pages; "IFTU Report on Activities 1944," 12 pages
  - Foreign - International Labor Organization (ILO), 1914-1971 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Five unsigned typescripts, "International Labor Organization" (one, "--and the AFL-CIO"), 1942, 1943, c. 1944, c. 1971, c. 1971; addresses by Rudolph Faupl, U.S. Worker Delegate to ILO conventions, 1966, 1967, 1968, 1970, 1971; statement by AFL-CIO Executive Council on 50th Anniversary of the ILO, February 23, 1968; address by AFL-CIO President George Meany "at an International Conference in celebration of the 50th Anniversary of the ILO," May 8, 1969, 5 pages; address by Meany to ILO Conference "on the Occasion of Its 50th Anniversary," June 12, 1969, 3 pages; transcripts of press conferences by Meany, 1971, 16 pages; notes
  - Foreign - ILO/World Health Organization, 1944-1949 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Letter to President Roosevelt from AFL President Green refusing to share ILO representation with the CIO, March 13, 1944, 3 pages; "Our Expanding International Relations," address by Assistant Secretary of Labor over CBS radio, August 3, 1946 re U.S. in ILO, 5 pages; articles; correspondence; notes
  - Foreign - International Labor Relations Department, 1935-1949 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Press release, AFL President Green protests purchase of German steel for construction of New York Triborough Bridge, November 1, 1935, 2 pages, with 2 page letter to WPA administrator attached; form letters (1938, calling for labor boycott of German goods and services; 1940, supporting German Labor Delegation to U.S.); letter from AFL official Matthew Woll announcing appointments to International Labor Relations Committee, February 18, 1944; letter from Woll re activities and finances of Free Trade Union Committee, March 24, 1949; "Report on Free Trade Union Committee," n.d., 4 page overview of the committee's history and ongoing activities; "Meeting for the Organization of the Trade Union Advisory Committee on International Affairs of the U.S. Department of Labor Confidential," 4 pages of minutes, December 12, 1946; audit of books of AFL Labor League for Human Rights, May 31, 1949, 5 pages plus cover letters; "Labor League Extends AFL Help Throughout the World," March 1949, 2 pages; notes
  - Foreign - Ireland, 1921 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Foreign - Italy, 1944-1956 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    Correspondence between AFL President William Green and Italian labor leaders, 1948-50; manuscripts containing: ("Members of the U.I.L. Governing Committee," 3 pages; translation of article from Il Popolo, official organ of the Christian Democratic Party, July 4, 1950; "Results of the Election of Shop Committees in the Past Few Months," 7 pages; "The Trade Unions Situation in Italy," signed by Italian labor leaders, May 1951, 7 pages; "Unione Italiana Larbro - Memorandum," c. 1950, 3 pages); "Draft Statement on the Italian Trade Union Situation," unsigned, April 15, 1952, 3 pages; "Report from Italy," from AFL representative Harry Goldberg, February 14, 1953, 7 pages; "Appendix to the Statement by Giulio Pastore, General Secretary, Italian Confederation of Labor Unions (CISL) - Submitted to the Executive Council of the AFL, February 4, 1954," 6 pages; photocopies of articles; notes; Italian booklets (3)
  - Foreign - Japan, 1937-1952 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    Telegram from AFL International Labor Relations Department Chairman Matthew Woll to U.S. Secretary of War Robert Patterson and Acting Secretary of State Dean Acheson and General Douglas MacArthur, protesting affiliation of Japanese trade unions with World Federation of Trade Unions, March 1947; confidential letter "to all International Presidents of the AFL" from AFL Free Trade Union Committee re "Growing Threat to Free Labor in Japan," July 1948, 2 pages; letter to Meany recommending strategy for countering WFTU activity in Japan, March 29, 1947, 3 pages; photocopies of articles; notes; AFL booklet,, "Japan's Soviet-held Prisoners of War," 1951, 33 pages
  - Foreign - Korea, 1948-1950 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    Letter from Labor Advisor to Seoul City Labor Bureau to AFL President Green re "get me out of here," July 1, 1948, 2 pages; statement by the Executive Council AFL re Soviet invasion of South Korea, recommending five-point program, August 10, 1950, 2 pages; AFL press release re military preparedness, July 17, 1950, 3 pages; clippings, notes
  - Foreign - Latin America, 1915-1963 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    Letters from AFL President Samuel Gompers, 1916 and 1919; "Report on Mexican Labor Relations and Affairs," by Matthew Woll, n.d. 6 pages; correspondence re "The Mexican Federation of Labor and Communist Propaganda," 1926-27, 5 pages; "Confidential Memorandum" to AFL President Green from AFL representative Robert Watt re Meeting with South American labor representatives in Santiago, Chile, September 11, 1942, 4 pages; "The Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs," unsigned, 1943, 5 pages; letter to U.S. Secretary of State from AFL representative Watt re improving conditions in Bolivian tin mines under U.S. contract, August 17, 1945, 2 pages; press release re AFL endorsement of Inter-American Conference, Mexico City, March 11, 1947; "Report on the International Labor Committee Meeting," January 6, 1948, re Lima Conference, 1 page; "Report of the U.S. Delegation" to Lima Conference, January 10-13, 1948, 9 pages; Hemispherica, bulletin of the U.S. Committee of the Inter-American Association for Democracy and Freedom, February 1963; "Romulo Betancourt, President of Venezuela: A Tribute On His Visit to the United States, February 19-23, 1963," by the Inter-American Association for Democracy and Freedom, 62 pages; clippings; notes
  - Foreign - Latin America, 1948-1970 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    "U.S. Labor Policy in Peru - Past and Future," by William A. Douglas, official (on leave) with AIFLD, c. 1970, 33 pages; "U.S. Labor Policy and Peru," prepared by William J. McIntire for the Adlai Stevenson Institute Conference on U.S.-Peruvian Relations, May 24-26, 1970, 36 pages; clippings
  - Foreign - Middle East, 1955-1970 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    "International Confederation of Arab Trade Unions: An Informational Note," translated from Sovietskie Prfsoyovsy, June 1970, 2 pages; clippings; notes
  - Foreign - NATO, 1953-1970 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    Clippings; booklet, "NATO: Its Development and Significance," by U.S. State Department, 1953, 50 pages
  - Foreign - Netherlands, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Foreign - Poland, 1942-1948 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    Several booklets published by Soviet government; notes
  - Foreign - Russia/Soviet Union, 1893-1955 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    Form letter to "trade and labor unions of America" from Samuel Gompers, opposing U.S.-Russian Extradition Treaty and supporting Russian patriots, March 15, 1893, 3 pages; cablegrams from Gompers and AFL Executive Council congratulating Russian patriots on victory over the Czar, opposing socialist, anti-democratic forces, April-September 1917; correspondence between Gompers and Secretary of State re U.S. recognition of Soviet government, July 1923, 7 pages; press release by Chicago Trade Union Committee for a Delegation to Soviet Russia, December 8, 1925, 2 pages; statement by AFL Executive Council opposing unauthorized labor delegation to Soviet Union, June 1926, 3 pages; "Memorandum for Mr. Green" re meeting with House steering committee on restriction of imports of Soviet commodities produced by forced labor, February 2, 1931; "The American Trade Union Delegation to Russia," [c. 1942], 3 pages; reports to "all International Presidents of the AFL," from the AFL Free Trade Union Committee, including "Confidential: What Moscow Thinks of Us," text of Soviet Overseas Service broadcast re AFL convention, December 1948, 3 pages; "Statement by the Executive Council of the AFL" opposing Stockholm peace appeal, August 1950, 2 pages; similar statement re Soviet peace proposal, August 7, 1951, 2 pages; "Sklavenarbeit in Russland," 8 page typescript in German: letters commenting on AFL pamphlet re slave labor in Russia, n.d.; "Statement by the Executive Council of the AFL" rejecting Soviet bid for U.S. labor delegation visit, August 10, 1955, 3 pages; notes; clippings.
  - Foreign - Russia/Soviet Union, 1943-1952 (Box 6, Folder 19-20)
    Russian-language booklets, some English-language, published by Soviet government
  - Foreign - Scandinavia, 1909-1953 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    Booklets and contract agreements published in Denmark, Sweden, Finland; notes
  - Foreign - Spain, 1946-1970 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    Press release: statement by AFL-CIO President Meany condemning the Franco regime, December 18, 1970; clippings, notes, booklet published in France re the Second Congress of Spanish Workers in exile (1946).
  - Foreign - Turkey, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    "A Trade Union Mission to Turkey" by AFL representative Irving Brown, April 17, 1951, 21 pages
  - Foreign - Vietnam, 1954-1970 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    Reprint of study for House Subcommittee on Foreign Operations and Government Information by Dr. Paul Taylor (signed: "For Phil Taft/Sincerely, Paul Taylor"): "Communist Strategy and Tactics of Employing Peasant Dissatisfaction Over Conditions of Land Tenure for Revolutionary Ends in Vietnam," 1970, 28 pages; two pages of tables hand-marked: "AFL-CIO Tet Relief," 1968; clippings; notes
  - Foreign - World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU), 1945-1948 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    Unsigned 3 page manuscript, probably speech, by CIO-associated author, March 1, 1945; "Trade Unions and Communism," issued by the Trades Union Congress Publicity Department, October 27, 1948, 3 pages; "World Federation of Trade Unions: Brief History," by Trades Union Congress, October 27, 1948, 3 pages; "TUC Expects No New Federation for Months" prepared by the American Embassy in London, February 9. 1949. 5 pages, ("secret"); press release by Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, countering protest by AFL re affiliation of German trade unions with WFTU, January 20, 1947, 5 pages; "Resolution on the Situation in Germany" adopted by the Executive Council of the WFTU on June &, 1947, 4 pages; "Report of the Commission of the WFTU to Investigate Conditions in Germany, c. 1946, 9 pages; "The WFTU Should and Will Live!" by D. Monin and M. Lazarev, from Trud, November 4, 1948, 4 pages; correspondence; notes; clippings
  - Foreign - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1944-1954 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    "Emergency International Trade Union Council - Summary of the Meeting held in London ... 14 September 1944," 12 pages; press release, AFL President Green criticizes World Trade Union Conference, the CIO, "and their Russian friends," February 19, 1945, 2 pages; statement adopted by the Executive Council of the AFL opposing World Trade Union Congress as Soviet-controlled, May 4, 1945, 7 pages; AFL Executive Council minutes re International Federation of Trade Unions, World Federation of Trade Unions, 1945-46; press release, "Declaration by Matthew Woll, Chairman, International Labor Relations Committee, AFL, on the breakup of the WFTU," January 21, 1949, 1 page; similar press statement, "Addenda," February 6, 1949, 2 pages; "Developments Since the WFTU Executive Bureau Meeting January 1949," Executive Board, May 17, 18, 1949, unsigned, possibly by CIO representative, 3 pages; "Report on WFTU, 1945-1949," Executive Board, May 17, 18, 1949, unsigned, possibly by CIO representative, 20 pages; three page manuscript "Copied From ... World Trade Union Movement July 1949 / The Fight Between Trade Union Imperialisms: T.U.C. Versus A.F.L."; "The WFTU's Third World Congress," by USRO representatives Diana Josselson and Morris Weisz, 1953, 10 pages; "The WFTU and the ILO," 2 page memo by Diana Josselson, with cover letter to State and Labor Departments, January 14, 1954; notes; clippings; publications.
  - Foreign - Yugoslavia, 1947-1950 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    Several booklets published by Yugoslav government, including two re Greece, 1947-50; "The Tito Regime: Declaration by the Executive Council of the AFL, May 11, 1950," 1 page
  - Fur and Leather Workers, 1901-1943 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Furniture Workers, 1876-1937 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    "Membership of Furniture Workers' Local Industrial Unions Chartered by CIO," October 9, 1937, 2 pages; notes
  - Gas, Coke and Chemical Workers, 1935-1942 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Form letter from AFL President Green; notes
  - Glass Workers, 1887-1942 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Booklet, The Bottle Maker, official journal of the Glass Bottle Blowers' Association, Volume 4, Number 2, August 1924; notes
  - Government Employees, 1888-1968 (Box 7, Folder 5-7)
    "Government Employees," unsigned manuscript, n.d., 42 pages; "Speech Before Convention of Teachers' Union, Chicago, August 22, 1957," unsigned, 14 pages; excerpts from reports of the Committee on Law of Government Employee Relations, American Bar Association, 1955, 1959, 1961 and 1963; "Agreement Between the City of Philadelphia and Philadelphia District Council 33, AFSCME," 1968, 18 pages; notes; photocopies of articles. See also: Strikes - Government Employees, Box 11, File Folder 5.
  - Government Employees - New York City, 1954-1967 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    Unsigned typescript re history of municipal employee relations in New York City, [1967], 3 pages; "Interim Order on the Conduct of Relations Between the City of New York and Its Employees," by New York City Mayor Robert F. Wagner, July 21, 1954, 8 pages; Executive Order #49, "on the Conduct of Labor Relations Between the City of New York and its Employees," [the Little Wagner Act] by New York City Mayor Wagner, [March 31, 1958], 5 pages; "Announcement of Procedures for Handling Requests for Certificates Under Executive Order on City Employee Relations," by New York City Department of Labor, June 23, 1958, 7 pages; "The City's Labor Relations Policies," by the Citizens Budget Commission, Inc. February 23, 1961, 8 pages
  - Government Ownership, 1883-1952 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Form letter; notes
  - Hair Spinners, 1888 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Hatters, Millinery, Etc., 1907-1952 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    "The United Hatters, Cap and Millinery Workers," unsigned typescript, c. 1952, 11 pages; correspondence between officials of AFL and Hatters re CIO affiliation, May-October 1936; U.S. Supreme Court opinion against Hatters, 1907, 21 pages
  - Haymarket Riot, 1886-1890 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Hod Carriers, Building and Common Laborers' Union, 1902 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Horse Collar Union, 1889 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Horse Shoes' Union, 1874-1921 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Hosiery Workers, 1933-1961 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Hotel and Restaurant Workers, Bartenders and Waiters, 1896-1943 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    Letter from President Green re jurisdictional dispute with CIO, 1943; notes
  - Hours of Labor, 1882-1963 (Box 7, Folder 18)